<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-02-24T12:57:11+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - The road to Chaiten</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - The road to Chaiten"/><published>2024-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter2/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_004-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_004-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_004-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_004.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Ferry crossing to Leptepu. </div> <p>The day started with a bit of rain, wet roads at the beginning and then a few drops started to fall when I was waiting to board the ferry. At the ferry pier, 4 other cyclists were waiting with bicycles much loaded than mine. Some of them coming from longer trips covering other countries in South America, and with different nationalities. In this road everybody is doing its own thing, you may be lucky and stick with a group but plans/goals are different for each cyclist. So this part of the trip is good to share ideas and experiences.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_005-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_005-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_005-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_005.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Sea farms. </div> <p>Getting to Caleta Gonzalo involves a long ferry trip to Leptepu (3.5 hrs), a transfer to Fiordo Largo (none can be left behind), and a final 45 minutes ferry. The day was cold with occasional rain as we transit between the continent and islands, and fjords. The coast was dotted with small houses and huts near salmon farms, some of these houses only reachable by boat. When the view to the west opened only sea could be seen, Chiloe is far enough that you may need to go up to higher ground for a distant view. The trip may seem tedious, but the few stops in the rain allowed me to take some pictures of the fjords with menacing clouds.</p> <p>For us cyclists, the transfer between ferries had two options. Since the high season was starting, the ferry personnel offer us to either cycle (the weather forecast said it wasn’t going to rain) or a bus. The second option meant we would have had to unload the bikes. However we were lucky, a truck carrying a few building tools had space for all the bikes and the driver was nice enough to carry them as they were. Hence, we just load the bikes and took the bus.</p> <h2 id="flying-through-pumalin-national-park">Flying through Pumalin National Park</h2> <p>The arrival to Caleta Gonzalo was cold, with sleet falling on the ferry, but just when we touch land the rain stopped. The first bad news were that the Pumalin National Park camping sites were closed, only the private one and the huts in Caleta Gonzalo were operating. Talking to my hostel host the day before I got the idea that you can still use the camping sites. What it really meant was that they weren’t maintained, so toilets may not have water and be dirty, but they were free. So three of us decided to risk it and continue since it was only 15:00 and the sunset was later than 20:00, but soon after I got ahead alone.</p> <p>There were some works on the first section of the road, so the gravel was bad, wet and with water accumulating in some sections. My only stops were to push my bike in the sections were work was being carried out and for a fast walk through the Los Alerces trail. The recommendation of my hostel host was to camp in the Camping Lago Blanco, but when I arrived there a backhoe loader was blocking the entrance. This plus being alone with occasional rain in a tent which I haven’t tested in rain for a long time, made push forward to the next camp site. Although there is a park ranger house at the next camp site, the situation was the same: no ranger and a closed camp site. So I made the decision to push forward to Santa Barbara.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_006-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_006-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_006-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_006.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The coast of Santa Barbara. </div> <p>The gravel road, which by that point was relatively good, finished soon after and in the tarmac my speed increased and arrived to Santa Barbara at around 18:00. In the only store open I bought some bread and asked for accommodation nearby. The owner told me that I could either camp in the beach, famous for its black sands and amazing sunset views or continue to Chaiten, a large town at mere 10km south. So I just made a quick stop by the coast (I saw the beach from the street, but stopped too late for a picture) and then pushed to Chaiten.</p> <p>My original plan was not to stop in Chaiten, but to make a quick stop to get food on my way to the other sector of Pumalin NP. So after arriving, the first thing to do was to find a place for the night. Since it was cold, I decided to stay at an hospedaje (something between hostel and hotel) and rest for one day.</p> <h2 id="not-quite-high-season">Not quite high season</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_007-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_007-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_007-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_007.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Chaiten and beyond with menacing clouds. </div> <p>On my day off I had a nice chat with the information center guide. Then I realised that many of my original plans weren’t going to be possible. Staying at the Ventisquero camp site in the Amarillo sector of the Pumalin NP was not going to be possible, as they were doing maintenance, and the only trail open was the Ranita de Darwin. So I meditated as I was walking around town, taking pictures and visiting the places affected by the volcano eruption. Given the closeness of the park to Puerto Montt, I decided to visit what I can and leave a longer visit to the park for another trip. With this in mind I was ready to push on to the south next day.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="9984516355" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Taking my time in Chaiten]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - Sunny start</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - Sunny start"/><published>2024-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter1/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_001-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_001-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_001-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_001.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Loaded bike ready for the adventure. </div> <p>After an over night trip by bus from Santiago, I finally arrived to Puerto Montt ready to cycle. The bus was late, an accident during the night implied that I was going to arrive almost 3 hours later than scheduled. Even so, sleeping in the bus was comfortable, no box needed to carry the bike and I still arrived during the morning. Puerto Montt is a nice city, but I have visited it many times, and at first sight not much have changed since my last visit in 2015. So my plan for the fist day was to get there, put the bike together and start cycling.</p> <p>The weeks before the trip involved a lot of preparations for the trip. Once decided that I was going to travel by bus, I bought food, gas for the stove and other camping/cycling gear. In the meantime, as I was getting up to the days with my parents the bicycle was being fixed. Just some minor but necessary changes, like brake cables, checking the gears were working properly, and then installing all the bike upgrades <a href="/blog/2022/trip_intro/">described before</a>.</p> <p>With all the gear together, it was time to load the bags. Of the three combinations I had in mind, I chose to load the front with camping gear (more on this later), and the rear for clothes, bike related tools, food and the tent. The bags ended up being quite even in weight on each side, so I felt very stable in the bike while loaded.</p> <h2 id="the-first-hundred-kms">The first hundred kms</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_002-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_002-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_002-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_002.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The small village of Lenca. </div> <p>Since I have started training for cycling more seriously around 4 years ago, I have grown accustomed to ride 100 or more kms in a day. With a loaded bike, the first day was a test of my ability and strength, more so if wanted to cover that distance after arriving late to Puerto Montt. After quickly assembling the bike and taking the customary pictures of the bike, I set off to the adventure.</p> <p>The day was sunny and relatively hot, which was expected as I picked the bus trip to start with good weather. Getting out of Puerto Montt was easy and fast thanks to the coastal cycle road. Just getting outside the city, I was “hit” by the change in pace from a big city like Santiago to a smaller one. Two horses were lose on the side of the road, so cars stopped while some people were trying to calm them and tying their leads to a fence pole. Nobody was honking, everybody was waiting peacefully, no stress.</p> <p>The road was relatively quiet, with views to the sea and mountains. Green soon was everywhere, in farms and forests. The road was dotted with mini markets, where I was able to refill my bottles and buy some snacks. A couple of freshly cooked seafood empanadas in La Arena where enough for lunch. Since the ferry was coming, I had them during the crossing, enjoying the views of the sea and the fresh air.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_003-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_003-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_003-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_003.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Ferry arriving to La Arena. </div> <p>The toughest part was a few kms after the ferry, where the road climbs through the forests. Here I was able to test myself and went full gas in one section, which I ended up walking the last few meters. If I had kept a good pace all the way I would have finish it up, but it’s good to know my limits. Getting to the end I was starting to feel a bit fatigued, just wishing to get to the last descent into town. This was mostly because I needed to get use to my position on the bike, being less aggressive than my road one. Luckily, I arrived at a good time in Hornopiren, when the stores were still open. Since it was the start of the high season, hostels where relatively empty, so even though I stayed in a shared room I slept alone.</p> <p>After the lessons learned this day I ended up more confident, but this was going to get tested immediately on the next day.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="9977705229" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The start of the Carretera Austral trip]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cycling around Taiwan</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2023/taiwan_trip_2023/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cycling around Taiwan"/><published>2023-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2023/taiwan_trip_2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2023/taiwan_trip_2023/"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/52644436340/in/dateposted-public/" title="The road and the sea"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/52644436340_2f291a2e4b_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="The road and the sea"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p> <p>This year I finally completed cycling around Taiwan without rest day and without train help. Here are a few details of this trip.</p> <h2 id="a-bit-of-history">A bit of history</h2> <p>This was my third time going around the island. The first time (2019), since I was just getting to know the roads in Taiwan, I followed what most tourist sites recommend: basically followed cycle route No. 1 with detours for Tainan and Hengchun and take the train to skip the Suhua road (between Hualien and Su’ao).</p> <p>The second time around (2021), I tried to follow roads close to the coast to complete the outer perimeter and visit the 2 lighthouses in the north and south tips of the island. However, due to weather, I had to trackback my steps from Kenting to cross through Mudan, instead of Manzhou, to Taitung. This time I was talked out of doing the Suhua road, mainly due to uncertainty on the weather forecast. After crossing by train I was a bit regretful because the weather was mostly fine with the exception of the last bit close to Su’ao, but I got to enjoy a more relax ride in the Taroko gorge.</p> <h2 id="this-time-around">This time around</h2> <p>For this trip, I tried to stick to the coast, which I achieved for the most part, and reach the extreme north-south points of the road (not necessarily the geaographical points).</p> <h3 id="the-equipment">The equipment</h3> <p>All my trips around the island have been with a light (more like bikepacking) setup. I used my road bike (<a href="/projects/cycling/">Merida Scultura 7000E</a>), so I cannot overload. My setup included a seat-pack from <a href="https://www.ortlieb.com/en_us/seat-pack+F9902">Ortlieb</a> and a top-tube bag from <a href="https://restrap.com/collections/the-carryeverything-range/products/top-tube-bag">Restrap</a>.</p> <p>The forecast included hot sunny weather in the south and a cold snap and rain for when I was getting close to the north, so I packed accordingly:</p> <ul> <li>2 bib shorts</li> <li>2 jerseys (1 short- and 1 long-sleeved)</li> <li>1 merino wool sleeveless base layer</li> <li>1 cycling waterproof jacket</li> <li>1 cycling windbreaker</li> <li>1 arm warmer pair (mostly for the sun)</li> <li>2 leg warmer pairs (one for the sun and one for the cold)</li> <li>2 pair of socks (one for colder and one for hotter weather)</li> <li>1 cycling cap</li> <li>Road cycling shoes and rain overshoes</li> <li>1 long sleeve t-shirt (that also served for sleeping and could be used as base layer if needed)</li> <li>1 sports trouser</li> <li>1 pair of trainers (light running shoes is this case)</li> <li>A pair of underwear</li> <li>Contact lenses and sunglasses</li> </ul> <p>In addition, all the necessary equipment to repair punctures, lube the chain and charge my electronic devices.</p> <h3 id="road-planning">Road planning</h3> <p>My trip started in Hsinchu, since it’s where I live, and travelled counterclockwise. I planned to follow the same road as the second try around the island, so mostly around the perimeter, but not necessarily visit the lighthouses because I had done that. As on every attempt I planned my trip around the Chinese New year holiday. This may not be the best time of year to do this trip. First, finding accommodation has to be done well ahead and the prices tend to go up. Also, the weather forecast kind be very uncertain, especially in the north. However, many cyclists choose this holiday for this trip, so it’s easy to find people to ride with.</p> <h3 id="west-coast-riding">West coast riding</h3> <p>The west side of the island has the biggest cities and is probably the most boring side (at least nature-wise). Since I visited them the first time around, I followed the coast road to skip most of the hassle of entering the city centre and save time and probably legs (less traffic lights).</p> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/52637662462/in/dateposted-public/" title="Lanterns"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/52637662462_b972cea5b5_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Lanterns"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p> <p>The first day I had a strong tailwind. It got a bit dangerous towards the end of the day, when I was crossing through small towns and the buildings produced strong crosswinds which almost pushed me down in my top heavy bike. The road along the Hsinchu and Miaoli coast is a mix of small towns, wetlands on one side and farms on the other and wind farms. After Miaoli, factories and the Taichung harbour dominate the landscape, making it a bit boring, while through Changhua and Yunlin counties farms are more common. Countryside houses have a different charm and sunsets with the sun reflecting in water pools or water in rice paddies are almost perfect for photography. This first day ended in the town of Tuku with a delicious <a href="https://www.tukuyicocoa.tw/">hot chocolate</a> and food around the city temple.</p> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/52640380175/in/dateposted-public/" title="Nankushen Temple"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/52640380175_4cc874fd77_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Nankushen Temple"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p> <p>The second day I still enjoyed a bit of tailwind, but the temperature was getting higher. Legs were feeling a bit sluggish at the beginning but by the end they were alright. The landscape on the first half is dominated by water pools for fishing and fishing harbour towns. After entering Tainan County, I visited a couple of huge temples. There are also salt fields that I visited last time around but this time I skipped. I passed through Tainan centre as fast as possible to reach the southern Tainan coast and then the industrial north coast of Kaohsiung ending in the Zuoying district with its popular tourist sites.</p> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/52642205783/in/dateposted-public/" title="Shadao"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/52642205783_308564d716_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Shadao"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p> <p>The final day on the west coast was hot, down to Kenting, but this was a very comfortable ride. The landscape transitions from industrial to sunny beaches and the ocean next to the right and green mountains to the left. A bit of headwind towards the end was not a problem to take in the landscape and fresh air. As usual during holidays, there was a traffic jam before the road split to Taitung, with some cars invading the cycle/scooter lane. Here I started to see more cyclists, some of them I will encounter later on the trip. At the end of the trip I dropped my bag in the hotel and cycle and walked to the southernmost point of Taiwan.</p> <p><strong>Distances and maps:</strong></p> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/8420836602">Day 1: Hsinchu to Tuku</a>: Mainly cycling routes No. 1, 1-4 and 1-5 (178 km)</li> <li><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/8425528652">Day 2: Tuku to Kaohsiung</a>: Mainly cycling routes No. 1-5 (160 km)</li> <li><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/8431243533">Day 3: Kaohsiung to Kenting</a>: Cycling routes No. 1, 1-19 and 1-20 (137 km)</li> </ul> <h3 id="east-coast-riding">East coast riding</h3> <p>The trip on the east coast is probably the most fun and full of green and fresh air. Even in bad weather the landscape is captivating.</p> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/52644253464/in/dateposted-public/" title="Taimali coast"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/52644253464_0ea14fdb8d_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Taimali coast"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p> <p>The first day on the east coast starts with rain and a bit of wind. The rain dominates the coast between Manzhou and Mudan with a bit dryer conditions when the road goes to the interior. This first half is also characterised by undulating terrain with a larger climb at the end. However after the climb and a good (but cold) descent, the rain stops and the road joins the 9 road so it widens and fills with cars. In this second half the safest thing to do is drive in the hard shoulder together with the scooters. The ocean is a constant on the right hand which can be seen from the top of the few ups and downs along the road. The day ends in Taitung with of my clothes almost dry.</p> <p>The second day on the east coast starts with a change of plan. Initially I was going to follow the coast road, but the cold snap brought strong winds and rain. In order to save the legs for the last two days (especially the longer last day) I changed to the east riff valley road. Once in the road I quickly realised that this was the best choice, because even with the protection of the coast mountains the headwind was strong and very rainy. The final bridge crossing into Hualien is horrible with the wind throwing small rocks a couple of times. At the end of the day the bicycle is dirty with almost no lube on my chain. Fortunately the motel where I stayed allowed me to use a hose to wash it and I quickly dried my shoes and clothes due to a perfectly positioned closet under the AC. To feed along the road in the next days, I went downtown to buy pastries and mochi in the many stores selling local produce.</p> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/52648397200/in/dateposted-public/" title="The road climbing from Heping"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/52648397200_498c2f7c63_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="The road climbing from Heping"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p> <p>For the Suhua road, the weather was not clear but it was favouring a drier day. I have heard different reasons why this sections is usually skipped, including: narrow roads next to cliffs with large trucks travelling up and down, and propensity for landslides particularly in bad/windy weather (once just happened a couple of weeks before my trip and collapsed a covered section between 2 tunnels). With people on holiday, less trucks go around the road during the Chinese New Year, so this seems to be the best season to travel along it. So I join forces with an American cyclist who I met in Taitung and decided to ride it. The cold brought some frost to the tip of the mountains, or at least the ones that can be seen under the clouds that most time cover them. We started the day early to avoid much of the traffic in the first few tunnels which are shared with most of the cars and are more narrow. After these tunnels the road divides between the old coastal one and the new one through tunnels (where bicycles are not allowed). Along the coast we didn’t see many cars, the road was empty for the most part with a few groups of people travelling by scooter. The road has different sections, each one ascending along the cliffs on the coast to then descent into a harbour town until reaching Su’ao. Each section has its own charms, but they all have in common the amazing views of the cliffs and the ocean. The final tunnel of the road is shared with the cars, which come and go in waves. This particular tunnel before the town of Dong’ao is wide and less risky than previous ones, but the descent at high speed is where the knowledge about cycling in Taiwan comes handy. By the time we reach the last section before Su’ao, a bit of rain starts to fall and the final descent is extremely cold, so we looked for some hot soup. After a few kilometers of riding along the coast of Yilan we part ways, and I reach my final destination for the day which welcomes me with a bit of rain.</p> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/52648403265/in/dateposted-public/" title="Dong&#x27;ao bay"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/52648403265_1f47120cae_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Dong&#x27;ao bay"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p> <p>The last time is the longest one and the longest distance I have travelled ever. It starts with an amazing sunrise out of the coast of Toucheng. Quickly I ride through the east coast of New Taipei and rush through Keelung. Here the road is dotted with fishing villages and geological parks. Once reaching the northern tip of Taiwan, when a bit of headwind starts to develop, a couple of riders pass me but I manage to stick with them and even share time on front to fight the wind. After the undulating terrain of northern Taipei and lunch, I continued solo through the flat road across the coast of Taoyuan. This was probably the most dirty (with rubbish accumulating on the side of the road) and worst tarmac of the whole trip. It is probably also the most boring section together with the Taichung one. It only improves after Yongan Fishing Harbour, which also has a nice bike path through the wetlands and a coastal path both of which I have visited before. Once in Hsinchu, I avoided the traffic through the river bike path, which is constantly improving and used by many people for exercise including some kids sprinting in their road bikes.</p> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/52650456565/in/dateposted-public/" title="Sunrise in Toucheng"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/52650456565_b146e9411f_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Sunrise in Toucheng"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p> <p>After passing the 200 km mark in one day, I felt that I could have continued, but there weren’t more roads to go in this trip.</p> <p><strong>Distances and maps:</strong></p> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/8437081334">Day 4: Kenting to Taitung</a>: Cycling route No. 1-20, 1-9, 1 and 1-6 (149 km)</li> <li><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/8442439324">Day 5: Taitung to Hualien</a>: Cycling route No. 1, 1-14 and 1-15 (167 km)</li> <li><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/8447914787">Day 6: Hualien to Toucheng</a>: Cycling route No. 1 (135 km)</li> <li><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/8453667478">Day 7: Toucheng to Hsinchu</a>: Cycling route No. 1 and 1-1 (220 km)</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="taiwan"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Chinese New Year cycling in Taiwan]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One year to go</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2022/trip_intro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One year to go"/><published>2022-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2022/trip_intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2022/trip_intro/"><![CDATA[<p>There is almost one year to go for my next touring trip. The destination is Chile to ride through the Carretera Austral from Puerto Montt to Punta Arenas (and maybe Ushuaia in Argentina). I have decided to document this trip including its preparation (route, equipment, resources), updates on the road and a final round-up. This first post is to introduce my preparation so far, so it’s basically focused on equipment.</p> <p>During the last 5 years I have been focused on road cycling, participating in a few <a href="/projects/cycling/">events</a>. So most of my investment has been on equipment that may not be suitable for touring cycling. However, I still have the bicycle and equipment that I used in my <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72157666638728105">last touring trip</a> in 2016. The goal now is to improve it and reduce weight.</p> <h2 id="bicycle-upgrades">Bicycle upgrades</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/bike_racks-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/bike_racks-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/bike_racks-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/bike_racks.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>In preparation for this trip I have decided to keep the gearing and do some maintenance. To carry things I want to have different options and decide later which combination of equipment I will use. For this I have upgraded the rear rack to a <a href="https://www.tubus.com/en/products/rear-carriers/tubus-product/logo-classic">Tubus Logo Classic</a> and got the <a href="https://www.tubus.com/en/products/front-carriers/tubus-product/tara">Tubus Tara</a> front rack. In addition, I have <a href="https://www.ortlieb.com/en_us/products/bike-bags/rear-panniers">Ortlieb</a> panniers for the front and back, a handlerbar bag, and added a <a href="https://www.ortlieb.com/en_us/rack-pack+K62H6">rack bag</a>. With these my options are:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Only rear loaded</strong>: use the rear panniers and the rack bag. In this case I would keep the tent inside the rack bag together with other equipment. The disadvantage of this system would be in case the tent is wet after rain (even though the tent has a dry bag).</li> <li><strong>Front and rear loaded</strong>: in this setup I would not use the rack pack and just strap the tent to the rear rack. Since the tent comes in a dry bag, rain shouldn’t be a problem. The disadvantage is that with the added storage space I can be tempted to bring more, making the setup heavier.</li> <li><strong>Use all</strong>: I hope I won’t get to this.</li> </ul> <p>The final combination will be decided once I have all the equipment (clothing, camping, etc.) and define what I want to use (based on weather).</p> <p>I will also upgrade the the bike tyres, going for a wider 700x35c (currently the bike is equiped with 700x32c). Here the options are Schwalbe Marathons (Plus Tour or Mondial), which are the prefered option for most people due to their durability and puncture proof, or Continental Contacts (Top Contact II, Contact Plus or Contact Travel). The size of the tyres may make them difficult to source them in Chile (where the 26’’ size is more popular), so currently I am searching locally (in Taiwan) or online for the foldable options of these to put them in my bag. Additionaly, I may need to change mudguards to keep my feet wet but no muddy.</p> <p>On the maintenance side, I will replace the gear and brake cables. Replace the front brake and brake pads.</p> <h2 id="camping-equipment-upgrades">Camping equipment upgrades</h2> <p>Here the goal is to go compact and reduce weight with respect to my previous equipment. Having more compact equipment will allow me to do bikepacking in the future, for shorter trips. My camping equipment include:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Tent</strong>: <a href="https://www.robens.de/en-gb/shop-1/outdoor-tents/starlight-2">Robens Starlight 2</a></li> <li><strong>Sleeping bag</strong>: <a href="https://seatosummit.com/products/spark-ultralight-sleeping-bag-series">Sea to Summit Spark 2</a> with the <a href="https://seatosummit.com/products/thermolite-reactor-liner">Sea to Summit Reactor Liner</a></li> <li><strong>Sleeping mat</strong>: <a href="https://seatosummit.com/products/ether-light-xt-insulated-sleeping-pad">Sea to Summit Ether Light XT Insulated</a></li> <li><strong>Stove</strong>: <a href="https://sotooutdoors.com/product/amicus-stove-with-igniter/">SOTO Amicus</a> which includes a 1 lt aluminium pot.</li> </ul> <h2 id="whats-next">What’s next</h2> <p>Between now and my trip I have to make a few decissions in terms of gear. I want to try my camping equipment at some point to make improvements well ahead of time. I will continue researching and informing any updates in the next few months.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Carretera Austral trip introduction]]></summary></entry></feed>