<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-05T10:54:52+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - Disconnecting from the world</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter12/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - Disconnecting from the world"/><published>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter12</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter12/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_059-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_059-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_059-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_059.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Esmeralda lake, just outside Cochrane. </div> <p>The road south of Cochrane looks like an isolated region in the maps, with a few established camping sites and more than 120 km to the closest town (Caleta Tortel). With a few gravel days on the legs most people chose to split this part in two, staying at the few available camp sites (most near the Vargas lake) or wild camping. Internet connection in this zone is almost none existent, just recently the established camp sites are starting to offer internet from Starlink. So planning and informing your plans to family is recommended, though not a must since the road is safe and there always people travelling along that can help in case of emergency. In my case, I decided to do something not many people do, which is have detour for some relaxing and isolation.</p> <h2 id="getting-to-los-ñadis">Getting to Los Ñadis</h2> <p>Right after I left Cochrane the rain started. Though it was mostly soft, using the rain gear up the first climb caused a bit of overheating. My first stop was caused by some road work, and once they let me go I had to push my bike a bit because due to the works and the rain I wasn’t getting much grip. From there, the climb arrives to a lagoon, where I took shelter under a tree for some pictures. At this time of the morning and with the rain it was feeling a bit colder as I was passing rivers over the hills.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_060-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_060-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_060-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_060.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Laguna Larga. </div> <p>Soon after the rain stopped and the roads were dry I got to a second stop. Here more cars were waiting, and I took the time to rest and feed a bit. The road passes through the hills or mountains with forest with smaller trees and several lakes at the distance. Close Los Ñadis, at the end of a slowly climbing road, it descends arriving to the Barrancos river. In this descent is where I saw my first huemul (deer), a female eating on the side of the road. The huemul seems not paying attention to me, so I could take a few pictures while I and some cars passed next to it. It is also in this descent that I saw the couple from Puerto Bertrand for the last time.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_061-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_061-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_061-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_061.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Huemul eating on the side of the road. </div> <p>Before the bridge across the Barrancos river, a junction indicates that I have to turn right for the less transited road to the <a href="https://www.instagram.com/refugiorionadis/">Refugio Rio Ñadis</a>. The road passes through big forests and a few farms separated by tranqueras (fence doors) that must be opened and closed so cattle and sheep don’t escape. Close to the Refugio, the road crosses a hanging bridge, the second one built here as the remains of a previous one still dangle in the river. My arrival at the Refugio is welcomed by some dogs and horses.</p> <h2 id="rainy-days">Rainy days</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_062-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_062-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_062-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_062.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Hanging bridge over the river Ñadis. </div> <p>My plan for my stay was to do two hikes and rest the final day to prepare for the next two tough days to Villa O’Higgins. As soon as I arrived I put my tent, even though the rainy weather forecast for the night and next day. Since The place offers camping and a refuge with beds, I planned to test whether the tent was still waterproof. All settled, I went for my first hike to the Caracol trail, which takes you high for a view of the junction of the Ñadis and Baker rivers, and the snowy mountains surrounding the place. I took my time in this trail, as the sun was bright and a few clouds were passing.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_063-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_063-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_063-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_063.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The rivers Ñadis and Baker from the Caracol trail. </div> <p>The second day starts with rain and the discovery that my tent wasn’t completely waterproof. With some of my thing wet, including the exterior of my sleeping bag and mat, I empty my tent and leave them drying in the kitchen. One of staff recommended me to go for a hike to the Paso San Carlos (an national monument built by the settlers of this region), and then later he would teach me to operate the wood stove. With some cookies and my camera in a small bag I started walking following the Baker river from afar with intermittent showers. As I passed several farms, the path was getting closer to the river. After the last one, I had to cross a small river bringing water from the mountains into the Baker. Passing implied jumping to avoid getting wet on the cold water. However a few hundred meters after, I arrive to another tributary. This one is more torrential, and difficult to cross as it had clearly grown from the rain and snow melting. A bit disappointed, I decided to go back because I was walking alone and didn’t have any change of clothes.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_064-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_064-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_064-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_064.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The Baker river on a rainy day. </div> <p>Once back, I passed by to visit the owner and to ask about how to use the wood stove. There I had the chance to meet everyone who worked in these nice place, and in proper southern Chile tradition, they invited me for a lamb stew. Later in the afternoon, they taught me how to operate the stove and cut logs. To stay away from the rain, I started reading some Chilean literature while resting in the now heated kitchen area. The rain was intermittent and every time it stopped birds, including parakeets, started to sing. With the stove I was also able to heat water for the bucket shower. At night, I installed myself in one of the beds in the refuge.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_065-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_065-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_065-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_065.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A newly born lamb. </div> <p>The last day, was a bit rainy in the morning but much less than the day before. I walked around the farms, down to the Baker, along the Baker and into the Ñadis river at their junction. Many sheep were around, with some just born, and some cows. After this long walk I finished the book and sorted my things already dry (including the tent). During our lunch I ordered a bread, which the owner said she will make if she had enough ingredients, and on the last day she came to the refugio to settle the bill, and to bring me a fresh out of the oven bread. This bread would keep me going for the next couple of days.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10147942395" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Relaxing and rainy days]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - Following the Baker</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter11/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - Following the Baker"/><published>2024-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter11</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter11/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_052-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_052-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_052-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_052.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Baker river at the confluence with the Nef river. </div> <p>The breakfast was plentiful, though the bread was a bit hard. Either way, it was a good start for a day full of cycling. The game of the day was basically to follow the Baker river, which starts from Bertrand lake. The river is a hot spot for people doing rafting or kayaking because of its rapids. The colour of the river is also its main attraction, as it changes along the way. At the start is deep green/blue, which I follow just separated by trees and every now and then holiday lodges or huts.</p> <h2 id="confluences">Confluences</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_053-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_053-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_053-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_053.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The Nef river at the top feeding the Baker at the bottom. </div> <p>The first big stop was to see the confluence of the Baker and Nef rivers. As a glacier fed river, the colour of the Nef is milky green like the Exploradores river, so at the junction the colour of the Baker changes to emerald. To get to this junction is necessary to walk through a well marked path, which I tackled after leaving the bike behind a bus stop (without lock). When I arrived there I was alone but on the way back a few tourists were walking to see the junction, two of them asked me how far it was. It turned out the two guys were a guy driving along the carretera and a cyclist who got bored of the gravel and was picked up by the other guy. As I was leaving the couple from the hostel in Puerto Bertrand was just arriving.</p> <p>So far the road had been flat, but soon after the first climb brought loose dirt and a machine fixing the road, but it felt that it was making it worse. I stopped a couple of times to look down to the river, which gets into a canyon in this section. I had food at the top of the climb, a long stretch of straight road between mountains without any forest, just shrubs. As the road was getting further from the river, the landscape turned more brownish.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_054-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_054-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_054-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_054.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Confluence of the Baker and the Chacabuco river. </div> <p>The next descent got me to the junction of the Baker and Chacabuco rivers. Right after the crossing the bridge over the Chacabuco river the next climb starts. I felt a car coming behind me, and it felt like they were waiting to see if I can get through the first hairpin which was really steep and dusty. Giving my previous experience in the cuesta Queulat, I kept calm and was able to climb without stopping. Near the top, the entrance to the Patagonia National Park told me I was getting close to Cochrane. Since I didn’t know whether the camping sites were open in this area of the park (which is managed by a different foundation), I didn’t plan to enter here. However, I stopped on the lookout next to the road for a view of the Baker canyon and the river junction from far up.</p> <h2 id="once-in-cochrane">Once in Cochrane</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_055-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_055-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_055-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_055.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Cochrane and beyond. </div> <p>Right after the top of the climb a steep descent section starts, which I took very carefully in case cars were coming the other way. Once the worst section of the descent is gone, the view opens to a valley with the Baker at its center and much greener than the hills where I stopped for food. At this point I was getting tired of the gravel for the day, but still some 10 km left to get into town. However 5 km before Cochrane new tarmac provided some respite for my tired legs and arms.</p> <p>Once again I arrived before 15:00, so I went directly to the main square and waited for the tourist information centre to open. This was the best decision, the guy in tourist information was very well informed. I told him about my plans, how many days left and what can I do around Cochrane. He finished convincing me that I should take the ferry between Tortel and Puerto Natales. With only one trip a week on Saturdays, I had 1.5 weeks to get there. Based on this he gave me several alternatives, around Cochrane these included visiting the Patagonia NP Tamango sector and also going to the Cayuqueo glacier. On my way south he recommended me to stop at Los Ñadis, instead of stopping at Lago Vargas.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_056-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_056-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_056-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_056.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Los Carpinteros trail following the Cochrane river. </div> <p>To visit the Cayuqueo glacier, I called several tour companies but they didn’t have enough people for a tour. Later I learned that I could have gone by bike and then take a boat to see the glacier. Either way, I set myself in the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/4VEXeiP3Hm67ijNE8">Camping Calafate</a> and talking to he owner, she recommended me to just go for the day to Tortel (the day of the ferry). So the first thing I did was to book the ferry ticket and contact the <a href="https://www.instagram.com/refugiorionadis/">Refugio Rio Ñadis</a> people to let them know I wanted to sleep there. The Refugio Rio Ñadis doesn’t have internet connection, so I was lucky I got a reply while the owner was in Cochrane stocking up. With my plans starting to settle, I walked around town to get dinner, buy food for my hike the next day, and visited the Cerro La Cruz lookout for a view of the town. Although the town has a brewery, in the information centre they didn’t recommend to visit at the moment because they were just starting to produce the beer. Either way when I passed by their restaurant it was closed.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_057-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_057-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_057-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_057.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Cochrane lake. </div> <p>The next day I took my bicycle and drove to the Tamango sector of the Patagonia NP. Many people, including the park rangers in the Exploradores, recommended to do the Carpinteros trail. Most also said that it was a good place to see huemules (deer). After registering and paying for my ticket I started walking. The camping site was close to the entrance and looked very quiet and well kept. Staying there was one of the recommendation from the park rangers in Exploradores, and I should’ve stayed there because the camping sites in town were much noisier due to the dogs. The trail follows the Cochrane river and wasn’t difficult. At the end you get to a lookout to see the Cochrane lake, a binational lake, and when I got there it was very windy. Although there are more trails that continue from there, the rangers didn’t recommend to continue because the last rain toppled some trees and some sections were blocked. On the way back I saw the couple of the Bertrand lake once again. At the end I wasn’t lucky with the huemules.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_058-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_058-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_058-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_058.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Cachaña (austral parakeet). </div> <p>Without a positive answer from the tourist companies doing the Cayuqueo glacier trip, I enjoyed the afternoon planning my trip to Los Ñadis the next day, and walking some more around town. Since the refugio was in a remote place, I had to get provisions, luckily the town has at least 2 big stores. I also informed my plans to my family because I wasn’t going to have internet access until the last town of the trip in around 5 days time. The last check of the weather forecast announced rain in the morning, so I moved the tent under the roof they had just finished installing in the camping site and went to bed.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10098205772" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10103139344" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The road to Cochrane and a hike]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - Goodbye General Carrera Lake</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter10/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - Goodbye General Carrera Lake"/><published>2024-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter10/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_048-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_048-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_048-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_048.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> General Carrera bridge. </div> <p>My fight against gravel started again after my long stay in Puerto Rio Tranquilo. At the beginning my legs felt a bit stiff, and I received news that the camping site I wanted to stay in Puerto Bertrand won’t open until next week. Generally, people camp in the beach of Puerto Bertrand, but I didn’t want to do that alone, so I planned a detour half way to Puerto Guadal to see if I can find something there.</p> <h2 id="to-puerto-guadal">To Puerto Guadal</h2> <p>The roads were a mix of good and bad gravel up until the Rio Leon (leon is how they call pumas in this region), where the road was similar to the one after Cerro Castillo. Nevertheless, the road continued next to the Carrera lake, going up and down. My first big stop was at the General Carrera bridge, where I had something to eat and walked around the hanging bridge. This is where the Carrera lake joins the Bertrand lake, and many people stop for a picture.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_049-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_049-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_049-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_049.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Puerto Guadal from the lake shore. </div> <p>Soon after passing the bridge the clouds started to build up, but the rain never came to lower the amount of dust I was getting from cars. Several lodges dot the road close to intersection where I took the detour to Puerto Guadal, 10 km away. During the climb to cross the hills I saw a condor pretty close flying and landing on the steep mountain side next to the road. The climb was neither difficult nor the highest one of the day, but it felt like if because of the sun that came out of the clouds. I arrived to Puerto Guadal before 15:00 so as usual all the stores were closed and the streets empty. I got to the coast to look back at the town, and decided to continue to Puerto Bertrand since it was too early. On my way back kids were playing in the main square and some school kids were walking along the road with their teacher for so what it looked like an expedition, giving a bit of life to this town.</p> <h1 id="to-puerto-bertrand">To Puerto Bertrand</h1> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_050-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_050-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_050-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_050.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Bertrand lake. </div> <p>Undoing the climb was easier from this side, but soon after descending to the intersection with the Carretera Austral another climb started. At this point I started to see the clouds building up again, with dark ones towards Rio Tranquilo. The road to Puerto Bertrand was probably the worst gravel of the day, very jumpy with big rocks coming out of the floor, something that I would only see again towards the end of my trip. This made the last descent into Puerto Bertrand very uncomfortable, and my hands and arms were really tired at the end, more than my legs.</p> <p>Puerto Bertrand is a small town, smaller than Rio Tranquilo and Puerto Guadal. With most of the people staying at fishing huts along the river, sleeping options were quite limited. As soon as I arrived I entered a cafe, where I got a slice of cake and coffee. There they told me about the hostel next door, and giving that there was a chance of rain, I decided to stay there. The lady in the hostel was very accommodating, and the room was nice. A couple also arrived to the hostel with a camper van, who I will see them again along my trip.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_051-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_051-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_051-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_051.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Caiquen couple around the lake shore. </div> <p>Without many things to do around, I walked around and tried to follow a hiking trail marked on the maps, but it was closed with a fence. I bought a souvenir and went to the second cafe in town for some food and ice cream. There people were talking about the stormy weather news coming from Rio Traquilo, it seemed that I left at the correct time. Although they said the bad weather may arrive here during the night, it didn’t happen.</p> <p>The rest of the day was spent on the lake shore where I took pictures of the caiquen birds and the lake as the sun was setting over the mountains on the other shore.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10098205423" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Getting closer to the mighty Baker]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - The end of tarmac</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter9/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - The end of tarmac"/><published>2024-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter9</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter9/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_041-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_041-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_041-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_041.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A rainbow in the Ibañez valley. </div> <p>The weather forecast predicted light rain early in the morning, but when I woke up it was menacing. So I quickly had breakfast and packed the tent while it was dry. When I came out of the camping site only wind and clouds were my companions</p> <h2 id="the-last-leg-of-tarmac">The last leg of tarmac</h2> <p>Straight out of town the first climb started. Once reaching the peak, amazing views of the Ibañez river and its valley. At the top the tarmac ends, and will only be seen aging in towns. Getting use to the gravel was hard. At the beginning I was over optimistic because the rain during the night packed the loose gravel, but this turn soon into worry when I descended back into the valley. Most of this section up until after the second climb was loose stones and very jumpy. The views where amazing though, with the soft rain in some parts of the valley producing rainbows.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_042-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_042-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_042-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_042.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Climbing out of the Ibañez valley. </div> <p>The second long climb of the day was not as complicated as the cuesta Queulat, and once the steeper part passed their were working renewing the road surface. The climb at that point was steady, but dusty and every time a car passed by a huge cloud will get up. At a point of the climb another cyclist caught me. With a lighter bike packing setup, he was training for a gravel competition and was going to Rio Tranquilo to visit a friend and then back to Coyhaique. We talk for a while and he pushed me to go faster, ensuring me that I was going to be able to get to Rio Tranquilo that day (something I wasn’t sure, given I didn’t have any experience about gravel). However at a point I got my wheel into a dust bank, losing grip, and soon he got away.</p> <p>I kept cycling even though it was almost time to have something to eat. So far the climb had been sunny, but closer to the top it got cloudy and colder. The best thing however was that, because of the rain, the gravel was packed and easy to ride. This let me descent on the other side very fast, so much so that I passed the other cyclist who was on the side of the road having a lunch rest, which I had done early in the descent. The road then was mostly dry but easy to ride and flat.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_043-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_043-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_043-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_043.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A view of the Carrera lake from next to the road. </div> <p>Soon the other cyclist caught me again and we ride together as we follow the river down to the Carrera lake. Although mostly flat, the road had several ups and downs, in one of which the other cyclist got ahead and I didn’t see him again. The landscape on this side was green with farms starting to appear as the lake was getting close. The color of the Carrera lake was between deep blue and emerald depending on the light and with the road right next to it for the most part. At this point, I was sure I was going to be able to get to Rio Tranquilo, so I relaxed a bit and enjoyed the views.</p> <h1 id="days-at-rio-tranquilo">Days at Rio Tranquilo</h1> <p>As usual, once in town I decided to get a camping spot in the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/GE5YusWfRCcrWHEg8">Bellavista Camping</a> who offers discounts for cyclists and the site looked well kept. Although the village is quite small, the amount of activities around are limitless. So, as soon as got all setup, clean and fed, I went to the lake beach were the local tourist operators have their stands. I registered for the “full-marmol” tour for the next day and Laguna San Rafael for the day after. Given the amount of activities available I decided to extend my stay in the camping.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_044-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_044-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_044-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_044.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Exploring the marble caves. </div> <p>The full-marmol tour consists of a boat trip to many small islands in the lake formed of marble which glimmer from the sunlight reflected on the lake. The tour also visits some shipwrecks in the lake. Given that the proper high season hadn’t started yet, the recommendation was to buy tours with the operators that have the most amount of people booked, because I they didn’t fill the spots the will drop you to other operator, sometimes last minute. So I did this tour with <a href="https://www.aoniexpediciones.cl/en">Aoni Expediciones</a>. Other way to visit the marble islands is by kayak, also offered by other companies, but the lake weather is complicated with stories of sudden changes in waves causing people in boats to get seasick.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_045-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_045-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_045-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_045.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Panoramic view of Puerto Rio Tranquilo and the Carrera lake. </div> <p>This tour was in the morning which left with the afternoon free to explore. Following the advice of other person in the camping, I went up hill to get a panoramic view of the village and lake. Finding the entrance to the path was a bit difficult, but a local told me how saw me a bit lost told me how to get into the path. The climb was fun, with a first section following a dusty forestry road to then follow a path into a pine tree forest and later into the more common landscape of shrubs and smaller trees. At the top I had a rest with a panoramic view of the lake and the mountains surrounding it. I was taking some pictures when a big shadow passed over me, a condor that was flying close. From this height I was able to see another condor flying over town.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_046-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_046-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_046-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_046.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> San Rafael glacier. </div> <p>The Laguna San Rafael trip the day after was very early in the morning and was organized by <a href="https://99aventura.cl/">99% Adventure</a>. We first had to travel by car to the Exploradores river mouth to take a boat down river, into the fjords and then into Laguna San Rafael. Laguna San Rafael is a lagoon formed at the feet of the San Rafael glacier, which comes down from the Campos de Hielo Sur ice field. We entered the lagoon and got as close as it is allowed to the glacier wall. On the way, big chunks of ice from the glacier went by us. Once there we had lunch and drinks cooled with ice from a small ice chunk. The return took a bit longer, because as the tides were lower the boat had to be more careful with sand banks while entering the river mouth. On the car ride back, we stopped at a waterfall and talking to the driver he gave some recommendations because I was planning to ride my bike on that road the next day. One recommendation I wish I knew before extending my stay in the camping was to camp near the National Park entrance for the Exploradores glacier, to then do the ~4 hour hike to the best viewpoint.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_047-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_047-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_047-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_047.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> View towards the Exploradores glacier. </div> <p>One of the tours that wasn’t available was walking on the ice of the Exploradores glacier, because of a crack they have discovered. So I decided to cycle to the National Park entrance. To get there, I followed the same road than the day before, which gets into the Exploradores valley. The day started with a close encounter with a martin pescador. Cycling through the valley I saw some animals popping out, at first they seemed like dogs as usual, but it turned out to be a bunch of rabbits that immediately started to run away. I stopped at the same waterfall than the day before, but this time the view was much better because the light in the morning was coming from the other side. Having done this road by car was useful, because I remembered the best spots for pictures. Once in the NP, I decided to do the shorter (30 min) walk to one of the viewpoints. Although far, the view to the glacier was clear but wishing to come back one day. I then talked with the rangers about recommendations for other NPs further south, one of those I came to regret not following.</p> <p>Back in town I prepared to be back on the Carretera Austral the next day.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10069190537" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10074015181" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10086579873" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[And we enter the gravel roads]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - A change of landscape</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter8/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - A change of landscape"/><published>2024-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter8/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_038-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_038-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_038-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_038.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The road out of Coyhaique. </div> <p>The road between Coyhaique and Villa Cerro Castillo is basically a long climb followed by a final descent. Some people break it into 2 days, but since it’s paved all the way and being well rested and trained (and pushed by my friend), I decided to do it in one day. Straight out of Coyhaique you notice the change in landscape, from the forests of the previous days to mostly pastures.</p> <h2 id="first-leg-to-el-blanco">First leg to El Blanco</h2> <p>I divided the day into 2 legs, the first one to El Blanco. This section is shared with many cars going to the airport, the biggest one in the region. The first part is a steady climb but for some reason it felt heavier than the one the day before, though it may have been the wind. The passes between mountains and in the distance you can see jagged hills, and cattle in the grass that covers the land all the way to El Blanco. After a quick descent I arrived to El Blanco at a good time, so I stopped in one of the stores in this small village to get water and a fast carbs from a Coke.</p> <p>Soon after El Blanco the road splits, one continuing to the airport in Balmaceda, and the other continuing south.</p> <h2 id="alone-in-the-mountains">Alone in the mountains</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_024-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_024-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_024-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_024.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Laguna Chiguay. </div> <p>Straight out of the bifurcation, 2 tourists waiting at a bus stop say hi and see you later. The road then starts to climb steadily and a bit steeper than before. At the time I was traveling, I saw a few cars going up, particularly in a section without pavement where I got all the dust lifted by them. As the road climbs, forests start to appear again and snow at the top of the mountains gets closer. My next long stop was a Laguna Chiguay, where I had lunch. A few people in cars also stop at this place and further up the road there is a camping that would have been a good place to stay, but it wasn’t open for the season.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_040-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_040-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_040-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_040.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Entering the Rio Ibañez province. </div> <p>A quick descent is then followed by the final climb of the day. This section of climb is not difficult, it being steady and long. The road now is almost deserted and the snow is next to the road. Although a usual place for seeing animals like huemules (deer), I didn’t see any. At the top of the climb I stopped for some pictures of the snow between the mountains. The descent into the Rio Ibañez valley was very fast and full of amazing views. Starting with the Cuesta del Diablo, a set of switchbacks that descent into the valley, and ending in fast almost straight road into Villa Cerro Castillo. Once in Villa Cerro Castillo, I searched for a camping.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_025-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_025-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_025-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_025.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Cuesta del Diablo. </div> <h2 id="days-at-villa-cerro-castillo">Days at Villa Cerro Castillo</h2> <p>Although I had contacted the owners of a camping site, once I arrived they told me they were actually 5 km away from town. In town only one was open, the one from <a href="https://turismoalgalope.cl/">Turismo al galope</a> at the end of town. Once again I was the only one in the camping, but some people arrived with camper vans. The owners told me some foreign cyclists had left the day before, so I was hoping to catch them further south. The town is small and walkable, and also have a couple of good restaurants serving huge sandwiches and small stores. There is also a cash machine at the petrol station.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_026-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_026-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_026-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_026.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Top of the mountains at the Cerro Castillo National Park. </div> <p>My plan for the next day was to hike to the lagoons up in the National Park. However, the path was closed because the snow hadn’t melt yet. The only path that was open was a short hike to one of the camping sites. Getting to the entrance got me some time because I decided to walk instead of riding the gravel road. When I was getting there a pickup truck driven by park rangers brought me to the entrance.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_027-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_027-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_027-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_027.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Towers at Cerro Castillo National Park. </div> <p>The hike climbs through coihue and lenga forest, with nice views of the peaks of Cerro Castillo. Few people were on the path, I passed a guide with Argentinian tourists which were going further (some trails were open only with a guide because of the snow), and on the way down a Brazilian couple. Back on the road I hitchhiked back into town (with the driver not recognizing my Chilean accent). Missing on the lagoons, I will have to definitely return to Cerro Castillo.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_028-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_028-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_028-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_028.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Jagged land. </div> <p>Before sleeping a look at the weather forecast for the next day indicated it may be rainy in the morning. Added were the almost 120 km to Puerto Rio Tranquilo, indicating that the next day was going to be a tough one.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10057073252" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10063091525" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A long day crossing the mountains]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - The Simpson river valley</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter7/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - The Simpson river valley"/><published>2024-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter7/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_021-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_021-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_021-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_021.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Hidden waterfall. </div> <p>On the last ride with the car with my friend down from his house, we visited a hidden waterfall down the river passing through the properties. Getting there was a bit tough, due the terrain and that the path was not marked, but only a short walk. Once back in the intersection with route 7, we said goodbye while some cyclists were passing by. The day was beautiful, sunny but not hot, and after riding for a while I passed the cyclists who where stopping at the top of a hill. I will see some of them at the end of my trip, but in the meantime I am on my own. Since the road was mostly descending towards Aysen, it took me no time to arrive to the intersection with the road connecting to Coyhaique.</p> <h2 id="waterfalls-and-the-simpson-river">Waterfalls and the Simpson river</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_022-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_022-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_022-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_022.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Cascada Velo de la Novia. </div> <p>The road to Coyhaique enters a valley, with steep hills to the left, resulting in a couple of waterfalls along the way, and the Simpson river to the right. After a few kms, I arrived to a restaurant that my friends recommended but it was closed on Mondays, once again due to the season. Many people warned my about this road, because many people travel between Aysen and Coyhaique, including big oil trucks and buses. So whenever I felt a truck was behind me, I moved to the side of the road. Either way, this wasn’t very frequent and the road was in good shape and dry.</p> <p>The first waterfall along this road was Cascada La Virgen. When I arrived a couple of cars were there, and it was very close to the road. On the other hand the second waterfall, Cascada Velo de la Novia, was a bit further and had to walk some 5 minutes, but more lonely. Both were impressive and let me stop for food a drinks. In between, the Conaf (park rangers) center was closed because, like any museum, they don’t open on Mondays.</p> <p>So far the road has been surrounded by trees, without many views of the Simpson river, but as I get close to Coyhaique the forest starts to disappear.</p> <h2 id="windy-welcome-to-coyhaique">Windy welcome to Coyhaique</h2> <p>With the Simpson river on my right, I start to see the climb waiting for me in order to cross to Coyhaique. Although not difficult, the climb seemed longer than it really is. The views of the valley I just crossed were amazing, however it was difficult to stop for pictures because there wasn’t much space to stop and some trucks were going up every now and then. Near the top, in Alto Baguales, I tried to find a nice spot but couldn’t find any. At this point the wind started to appear, and so the wind turbines, making it colder than in the valley below.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_023-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_023-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_023-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_023.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Coyhaique from lookout. </div> <p>After a quick stop at the Marchant lookout for some pictures of Coyhaique, the road descended into town. The descent was fast, with the wind pushing sometimes. Once in town, the first task was to look for a camping. The one my friend recommended was unfortunately close, maybe because of the season or maybe because I arrived before 15:00. So I headed to the town main square where a guy managing a touring station gave some recommendations of camping sites and about the road further south. The second alternative was open, but they were one week away from opening the camping, as they were just refurbishing it when I arrived. However, they offer me a room for the price of a shared room (another advantage of the almost high season), so I stayed there, in the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/AvzNyWGMGvwGSyAU8">Aldea Patagonia</a>.</p> <p>After a wash and a change of clothes, I walked around Coyhaique. There were many people in the city center, many students just coming out of schools. I stopped for ice-cream before buying a gas canister, that at the end of my trip never used and had to give it away, and consulting about bike boxes in a cycling store. At this point I wasn’t sure how the trip was going to end, whether I was going to continue south by ferry or come back by bus/cycling and leave from the main airport located near Coyhaique. Since it was before Christmas, they told me I was more lucky to find a box, as they stock more bikes. It turned out that I didn’t come back to Coyhaique, but it was good to know.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_037-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_037-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_037-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_037.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Simpson river next to Coyhaique. </div> <p>Since I got food for a few days in Aysen, I didn’t need to visit any supermarket. So the rest of they I spent it walking around and buying something for dinner and breakfast next day. There are a few things that can be visited around Coyhaique, but I didn’t want to stay in a relatively large city. My plan for the next day was to ride the almost 100 km to Villa Cerro Castillo, banking on the rest days at my friend’s house and a good night sleep.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10050821439" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A day for waterfalls and a climb]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - Time to visit friends</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter6/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - Time to visit friends"/><published>2024-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter6/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_035-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_035-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_035-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_035.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Walking along Cisnes river. </div> <p>The day started with a bit of fog but quickly going away, and a walk along the Cisnes river. The shore of the river along the <a href="https://www.refugioriocisnes.com/">Refugio Río Cisnes</a> has a well marked path, which I explored while my tent was drying. Packing took me a bit more time than expected, because of the grassy field. Once packed was time for breakfast with a brownie and other treats from the cafe. With all done, it was time to get back on the saddle.</p> <h2 id="the-road-to-villa-mañihuales">The road to Villa Mañihuales</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_018-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_018-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_018-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_018.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Lago Las Torres </div> <p>Soon after getting out of the camping the road starts to climb what it was the toughest climb of the day. At the top Villa Amengual appeared, which give me the opportunity for a first quick stop. Soon after a quick descent, another chance to stop at Lago Las Torres, a beautiful lake surrounded by forests in a Natural Reserve. The road continues through the forest and slowly some farms start to appear until the road gives way to a valley with larger farms with horses around. Getting closer to Villa Mañihuales most farms are clearly marked by alamo trees, and the hills start to get dotted by flowers from the spring that is just starting. Once in Mañihuales I got lunch while I waited for my friend to pick me up in his car, as his place is a bit far and without easy access.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_019-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_019-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_019-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_019.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Laguna Esponja at Villa Mañihuales </div> <h2 id="a-weekend-with-friends">A weekend with friends</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_036-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_036-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_036-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_036.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Cascada del Leon. </div> <p>For a long deserved rest, I spent a weekend with a friend from university and his wife. They received me in their small but charming house near Mañihuales, with their 3 dogs, chickens and their 2 newly arrived horses (a mare and its foal). I enjoyed their cooking and we visited Puerto Aysen, for them it was a monthly trip to restock and for me to get snacks for the following days. We took a detour on our way back to visit a waterfall for a lunch/picnic.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_020-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_020-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_020-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_020.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Coihue forest. </div> <p>My friends’ place is surrounded by forests and mountains, which made the Internet connection a bit difficult. We took advantage of the surroundings for a hike and get their dogs a good walk. The hike took us through a river crossing (where I lost one of my flip-flops), with freezing water from the melting snow, to then follow the path used by forest workers and farmers to move cattle. The forest is full of coihue and, at higher altitudes, lenga trees. There were also traces of burnt trees from the times these valleys were settled, not by indigenous peoples but by Chileans trying to tame these lands. As the path crossed several private lands, it was quiet but we didn’t have the chance to see anything else than some birds. The final crossing of the river that run across all the private lands was a bit more difficult, but lunch was waiting on the other side.</p> <p>Thanks to my friends, I got a good rest and a warm up for the following days where I included a couple of 100 km rides in succession (something my friend convince me I was capable to do).</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10033204945" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A ride and a weekend with friends]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - Fully pack day</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - Fully pack day"/><published>2024-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter5/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_014-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_014-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_014-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_014.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Laguna Tempanos and the Ventisquero Colgante, Queulat National Park. </div> <p>The day started as planned. A cold early morning breakfast, not in a rush but moving around to sort things and to keep warm. After packing my tent and loading the bike, I enjoyed the sunrise in the small beach of the camping site and saw a couple of toninas getting into the fjord. To continue warming up, I headed to the Queulat NP entrance and arrived a bit ahead of the opening. There workers were arriving and preparing to continue with the access road maintenance.</p> <h2 id="the-ventisquero-colgante">The Ventisquero Colgante</h2> <p>The entrance to the NP was smooth. To access the park reservations were necessary but payment had to be made at the entrance. I was amongst the first group of people to enter the park, together with a couple of Chilean friends and a couple of foreign tourist. After a quick debrief about which trails were open, I parked my bike and prepared to walk. First to the lagoon (Laguna Tempanos) were I got a clear view of the glacier, but as was taking my last pictures a cloud started to form in front of the glacier.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_033-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_033-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_033-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_033.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Ventisquero Colgante covered by clouds. </div> <p>I calculated that I had to leave by noon if I wanted to arrive at a good time to my next destination or in case I had any accident or longer than predicted stop. So if I wanted to reach the lookout closer to the glacier I would had to run a bit. With the pressure of time and the clouds forming on the mountains, I rushed to the lookout. Even at a faster pace, I stopped at the few lookouts on the way, and even to listen and record a woodpecker singing. The trail is relatively steep at the beginning, but after the climb it goes relatively flat with smooth ups and downs. When I arrived to the lookout the hanging glacier was covered, only the water falling could be seen below the clouds. Knowing the trail and that descending is usually faster, I waited for a while. A friend told me that he waited for a couple of hours, I didn’t have that much time, but I was satisfied after seen it from the lagoon. I waited long enough that people I passed by on the way up and tourists that arrived later caught with me, then I rushed on the descent.</p> <p>On the way down I saw a couple of foreign tourist, not quite convinced with continuing up, and one of the cyclists I met on the ferry of the second day. Since he was wearing a lot of clothes in the ferry, I didn’t recognized him, so in my rush down I only said hi and ask how he was doing. Arriving at the parking I saw his bike and realized it was him. I arrived to the parking at noon, had something to eat, refilled the water bottle and headed out.</p> <h2 id="gravel-and-amazing-roads">Gravel and amazing roads</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_015-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_015-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_015-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_015.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The top of the *cuesta* Queulat. </div> <p>The paved road was soon replaced by gravel as the road started to travel along the Queulat river. The section before the <em>cuesta</em> Queulat had some paved sections, part of unfinished works done by a company that ran out of business during the pandemic, though some people said the company wasn’t the best for the job even before. Either way, these sections provide a bit of calm from the jumpy road. With a wide river head joining the sea at one side, many people say that toninas can be seen in that section, but I wasn’t lucky or maybe I was too late. As the road was approaching the <em>cuesta</em>, I was thinking what would I do I had a mechanical or wasn’t able to continue. The road seemed at that point very solitary and quiet, so my mind was going to dark places even in a bright day.</p> <p>The <em>cuesta</em> Queluat is a series of hairpins that climb some 500 m over 5 km in the toughest part, and some people say the most difficult part of the Carretera. As soon the first hairpin arrived I got into some problems. There you can find a path to a waterfall, so I stopped to the side of the road but couldn’t find a place to leave the bike (my bike doesn’t have a kickstand). Even keeping the bight up straight was difficult, more so getting back on the saddle, because the road was dry and covered by loose dust with little grip. It turned out most hairpins were like this, and in some of the lower flatter sections the dusty roads felt like riding in sand. So much so, that I had to stop in a section because I couldn’t keep up straight and a driver in small truck coming behind me offered to carry me, but the climb was just starting so I just said thank but I was going to continue trying. Knowing that people are kind in this part of of the country helped to overcome those dark thoughts I had in the middle of nowhere.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_034-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_034-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_034-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_034.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Puntiagudo from the road next the Cisnes river. </div> <p>After a few hairpins I got a grasp of how to face them, basically going wide and not getting in my lowest gear. By the top, they were less dusty. I saw a few more cars going up and down, but this time not being completely on the high season was in my favour because even with these few cars I got to cross their dust clouds. Closer to the top the views got better, with snowy peaks on each side and a bright day throughout. At the top also, the road was was replaced by brand new tarmac, so the descent to the Cisnes river valley was very smooth.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_016-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_016-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_016-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_016.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Empty roads and snowy mountains. </div> <p>The ride down to valley had some amazing views, so were the views in the valley. Here the road follows the Cisnes river into an open valley with some large farms and surrounded by breathtaking mountains. The next town along the road was Villa Amengual. Although some people recommend to stay there, it seems that there aren’t any camping sites and hostels are not the best. A cyclist refuge use to be in the village, but some people reported that it burned down and that the current status is not as good. So I considered two other camping sites before the village.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_017-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_017-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_017-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_017.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Cisnes river, near the camping site. </div> <p>The first one I passed soon after getting into the valley, but I only considered this one as a backup if I was running late. The second one was recommended by the owners of the hostel in Villa Santa Lucia. I contacted the owners of this camping when I stopped in Puyuhuapi, as I learned that some places were still closed. The camping (<a href="https://www.refugioriocisnes.com/">Refugio Río Cisnes</a>) is a large place next to the Cisnes river. I was the only one camping that night, but days before a large group of foreign cyclists had passed by. This was one of the best camping sites on the Carretera Austral. The camping has a cafe for people traveling by other means, where they offer food. Most of the reviews recommend their pizzas, however when I arrived they didn’t have the ingredients so they were out buying. Nonetheless, their cinnamon buns were amazing and their sandwiches replenished my energy levels after a long day on the saddle.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10027607985" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A hiking and cycling day]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - The long wait</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - The long wait"/><published>2024-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter4/"><![CDATA[<swiper-container keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_011-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_011-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_011-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_011.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_030-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_030-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_030-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_030.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <div class="caption"> Rosselot lake and confluence of Palena and Rosselot rivers. </div> <p>After a few days cycling with a loaded bike I had become aware of how many kms I could cover each day. So I estimated that going that getting to Puyuhuapi would be a breeze. This gave me some time to visit the places I had planned to visit the day before and couldn’t because of the rain. The owner of my accommodation let me leave the bags there, so I traveled light to a couple of places. First I visit the Rosselot lake. After the road through Pumalin, this was the second time I would ride on gravel, but this time the gravel was more similar to what I found further south. Getting to the lake didn’t take too much time and the gravel wasn’t that bad. There aren’t any walking path around the lake, but there is a small pier from where one can walk along the shore. The lake is surrounded by green mountains and many birds can be seen in the beach. After a walk and some pictures, I headed back the same road and then to the second place, which was the confluence between the Palena and Rosselot rivers. To get there I parked my bike next to the road and crossed a fence used to keep cattle off the road. The confluence is not as majestic as the ones of rivers south of Coyhaique, but still worth a short visit.</p> <h2 id="heading-to-puyuhuapi">Heading to Puyuhuapi</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_012-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_012-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_012-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_012.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Puyuhuapi from Los Canelos Trail. </div> <p>After this short adventure on gravel, I returned to the hostel to get my bags and resume my trip south. The road to Puyuhuapi was flat with a couple of gravel sections where landslides went through the road. Since I started later than previous days, I had a stop for lunch on the side of the road around Risopatron lake. By that time the cold head wind and passing clouds that were present leaving La Junta subsided and the day was now bright and sunny. Soon after lunch I arrived to Puyuhuapi, so I headed to a cafe for dessert. Puyuhuapi is a small town located in the coast of a fjord that is well protected from the sea, so the waters are quiet. The turn to use my tent had finally come, I installed myself in one the camping sites in the coast (one was closed and didn’t ask in the third one). I was alone in the camping, but the owner told that another cyclist left during the morning.</p> <p>Similar to La Junta, there is an easy hike to get a panoramic view of the town and the fjord. The trail goes through the side of a hill and is home of many canelo trees (hence the name of the trail). Since the days before were rainy and cattle usually use the trails, the top of the trail was muddy. Nonetheless, the views at the top were worth the dirt in the shoes. Back in town I walked around and bought bread, striking a conversation with the bakery owner. He shared with me some stories (like one were a cycling tourist was strangely attacked by a puma during winter) and advice for the road south.</p> <h2 id="long-wait">Long wait</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_031-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_031-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_031-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_031.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Canelo tree. </div> <p>The morning next day was very cold, the coldest during this trip, with temperatures below zero. In the camping I had my first experience turning on the wood stove, but I didn’t succeeded without the help of the owner. The Queulat NP was closed a three days a week due to road work on the park, which meant I had to wait one more day around Puyuhuapi. So I decided to move to a camping site closer to the park (the camping site inside the park was also not working). These campings were just a few kms from Puyuhuapi, so I just took my time defrosting/drying my tent with an incipient sun light. Before leaving the town, I enjoyed a last visit to the cafe to have a kuchen and hot coffee.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_013-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_013-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_013-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_013.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The road next to the fjord. </div> <p>There were two working camping sites near the park, my first option was slightly after the entrance of the park (further away from Puyuhuapi). When I got there, the toilets and showers looked clean, but the sites were not quite ready and you can see that sheep had used them recently for protection. So I went to the other option, which was before and further back from the entrance to the park. The camping was really nice, with access to a small beach where later that day I saw a martin pescador (common kingfisher), and the next morning the fins of a couple of toninas (Chilean dolphins) going into the fjord for breakfast.</p> <p>So far my food planning had been very poor, I still have food that I brought from Santiago and hadn’t used my camping stove. Bread had been available throughout the trip, and restaurants/cafes were easy to find. However there weren’t any stores near the camping site, the closest one were I was able to get bread (actually quite big ones) was in front of the other camping site. Learning this from one of the workers in the camping site, meant I had to travel there and back once again. It turned out that this would be enough for breakfast and a couple of days to keep me fed on the bike.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_032-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_032-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_032-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_032.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Sunset at Puyuhuapi fjord. </div> <p>Here I planned my next day, which was going to be quite hectic. The plan was to wake up early to arrive as soon as the NP opens, hike to the overlook and then continue my trip around noon. With 60 km separating the NP and the camping site I planned to stay the day after, including a gravel section with a “cuesta” that many people think is the most difficult of the whole trip, this was going to be the day I would arrive the latest to my next stop so far. Without artificial light in the camping, I went straight to sleep after enjoying an amazing sunset.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10014575244" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10020435369" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling stuck]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carretera Austral - The valley of rain</title><link href="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carretera Austral - The valley of rain"/><published>2024-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://folguinch.github.io//blog/2024/carretera_austral_chapter3/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_029-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_029-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_029-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_029.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Hanging bridge over Yelcho river. </div> <p>The day started once again with rain. Straight out of Chaiten three dogs were following me and barking, but none had enough stamina to keep up with me. After this scare, the road was quite quiet, with not many cars or trucks. So far, they have been well behaved and passed me respecting the 1.5m of distance. Many locals told me to be careful, but drivers were more careful maybe because the proper high season hadn’t started yet. What would turn out to be a common thing along this trip is that drivers on the other direction waved to say hi. Even people on motorcycles (many of them Brazilian tourists) were also saying hi.</p> <p>The first stop of the day was at the Ranita de Darwin trail in the Amarillo sector of the Pumalin NP. Nobody was here, only some boot marks on the dusty road indicated the presence of someone somewhere. With nobody in sight, I quickly did the trail. The trail itself is a path through the forest sometimes muddy but with wooden planks to cross some of them. Seen a Ranita de Darwin is very difficult as they are very small, however I saw woodpeckers and other birds could be heard.</p> <h2 id="rain-and-cold-on-the-rise">Rain and cold on the rise</h2> <p>With a bit of rain every now and then, water falling from the mountain sides could frequently be seen from El Amarillo to the south. The first big lake on the road is the Yelcho. So far the road hasn’t been difficult but once you reach the lake it starts to climb. The lake cannot be seen much once you pass the hanging bridge after Puerto Cardenas because of tall trees, the few lookouts are not very good as the electricity cables block the view.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_008-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_008-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_008-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_008.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Water from the Yelcho Glacier on the cuesta Moraga. </div> <p>The first big climb is the “cuesta” Moraga. This climb is not difficult, but closer to the peak patches of snow could be seen on the side of the road. The cold and rain, made for a very cold descent into Villa Santa Lucia. This small village was almost erased from the map after a landslide, caused by high temperatures and rain near the Yelcho glacier, buried part of the town on 2016. The consequences can still be seen as a section of the road is still being repaired and in the museum dedicated to the tragedy.</p> <p>As a small town, there were 2 hostels, a camping and some cabanas. Although the camping was covered, a few pools of water were under the roofs. Of the 2 hostels, the owners of my preferred ones were out and hadn’t come back. So I went to the other one, because the cold was setting in (but was still relatively early). The hostel wasn’t well kept, understandably because the owner may have only time for the store in the first floor. After showering and having a soup, I went to my room to rest. Here I noticed that the room was not the best, with a hole in the wall (which I covered with tape) and holes in the roof were some bird poop has accumulating.</p> <p>So I decided to give the other place a go. Fortunately, the owners were back, so I moved there. This one was more comfortable, and I spent a good time talking to the owners, who shared stories about other travelers and how was living through the pandemic here. They also gave some recommendations about good camping sites to stay further south.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_009-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_009-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_009-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_009.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Araucaria (monkey puzzle tree) at La Junta square. </div> <p>The next morning was raining more heavily and colder, but the road was very flat and it took me little time to arrive at La Junta.</p> <h2 id="days-at-la-junta">Days at La junta</h2> <p>La Junta is a bit smaller than Chaiten, but the dogs were tamer. At the time of my arrival it was getting sunny with scattered clouds and windy. After a well deserved lunch I found accommodation. There was no point on rushing since the next national park I wanted to visit would be closed for a few days before I could get there. So I stayed in a good place for 2 nights.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/carretera_austral_010-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_010-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/carretera_austral_010-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/carretera_austral_010.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> La Junta from lookout. </div> <p>After putting my clothes and cycling shoes to dry and taking a good shower, I walked to a lookout in the hill next to town for a panoramic view of the town. With passing clouds beams of light illuminated the green fields in the farms around town and the snowed mountains at the distance. I spent probably a good 30 minutes there enjoying the view and taking pictures. Food in town was not easy to find with only a couple of restaurants and stores open. Nevertheless, I enjoyed the local salmon, puyes (small fish which are locally produced and sold at high prices to international hotels) and nalca (giant rhubarb) as dessert.</p> <p>The good weather didn’t last. The day after I was thinking of going to the Rosselot lake and visit the confluence of the Palena and Rosselot rivers, but the rain started early and didn’t stop until the end of the day. Even going out to get food without getting wet was difficult. So I just rested that day and sorted my things.</p> <h4 id="maps">Maps:</h4> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="9996753792" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <div class="strava-embed-placeholder" data-embed-type="activity" data-embed-id="10002580630" data-style="standard"></div> <script src="https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js"></script> <p><br/><br/></p> <h4 id="more-pictures">More pictures:</h4> <p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/faoch/albums/72177720313509568" title="Carretera Austral"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53409424323_e204897c05_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Carretera Austral"/></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><category term="cycling"/><category term="trips"/><category term="carretera-austral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Days of rain and cold]]></summary></entry></feed>